[Music]
Reedman reads
The Giver by Lois Lowry, narrated by Fraser Reedman.
Chapter 21.
It would work.. They could make it work,.
Jonas told himself again and again throughout the day..
But that evening, everything changed..
All of it—. —all the things they had thought through so meticulously— —fell apart..
That night,, Jonas was forced to flee..
He left the dwelling shortly after the sky became dark in the community still..
It was terribly dangerous because some of the work crews were still about,. but
he moved stealthily and silently,, staying in the shadows,, making his way
past the darkened dwellings in the empty Central Plaza, toward the river.. Beyond
the Plaza, he could see the House of the Old, with the Annex behind it, outlined
against the night sky.. But he could not stop there.. There was no time.. Every
minute counted now,, and every minute must take him farther from the community..
Now he was on the bridge,, hunched over on the bicycle, pedalling steadily.. He
could see the dark, churning water far below.. He felt, surprisingly, no fear, nor
regret at leaving the community behind..
But he felt a very deep sadness, that he had left his closest friend behind.. He
knew that in the danger of his escape, he must be absolutely silent;. but with
his heart in mind,, he called back and hoped that with his capacity for hearing
beyond, The Giver would know that Jonas had said goodbye.. It had happened at the
evening meal. Lily chattering away,, Mother and Father making their customary
comments (and lies, Jonas knew) about the day..
Nearby,, Gabriel played happily on the floor,, babbling his baby talk,, looking
with glee now and then toward Jonas,, obviously delighted to have him back
after the unexpected night away from the dwelling.. Father glanced down toward the
toddler.. "Enjoy it,, little guy,"," he said..
""This is your last night as a visitor."."
""What do you mean?"?" Jonas asked him..
Father sighed with disappointment..
"Well,, you know, he wasn't here when you got home this morning because we had him
stay overnight at the Nurturing Center.
seemed like a good opportunity, with you gone, to give it a try.. He'd been
sleeping so soundly.". "Didn't it go well?"?
Mother asked sympathetically.. Father gave a rofful laugh.. "That's an
understatement.. It was a disaster.. He cried all night, apparently.. The night
crew couldn't handle it.. They were really frazzled by the time I got to
work.". "Gabe,, you naughty thing,"," Lily said, with a scolding little cluck toward
the grinning toddler on the floor.. ""So,"," Father went on,. ""we obviously had to
make the decision.. Even I voted for Gabriel's release when we had the
meeting this afternoon."." Jonas put his fork down and stared at his father..
""Release?"?"
he asked..
Father nodded.. ""We certainly gave it our best try,, didn't we?"?" ""Yes,, we did,"."
Mother agreed emphatically.. Lily nodded in agreement,, too.. Jonas worked at
keeping his voice absolutely calm..
"When?"? he asked.. "When will he be released?"? "First thing tomorrow morning..
We have to start our preparations for the Naming Ceremony,. so, we thought we'd
get this taken care of right away.. "It's bye-bye to you,, Gabe,, in the morning.
Fatherhead said, in his sweet singong voice..
Jonas reached the opposite side of the river,, stopped briefly,, and looked back..
The community where his entire life had been lived lay behind him now, sleeping..
At dawn,, the orderly,, disciplined life he had always known would continue again,
without him.. The life where nothing was ever unexpected. Or inconvenient. Or
unusual.. The life without color,, pain,, or past.. He pushed firmly again at the
pedal with his foot and continued riding along the road.. It was not safe to spend
time looking back.. He thought of the rules he had broken so far:, enough that
if he were caught, now,, he would be condemned.. First,, he had left the
dwelling at night., A major transgression.. Second,, he had robbed the
community of food:, a very serious crime,.
even though what he had taken was leftover, set out on the dwelling doorsteps for collection..
Third,, he had stolen his father's bicycle.. He had hesitated for a moment,,
standing beside the bike port in the darkness,, not wanting anything of his
father's, and uncertain, as well, whether he could comfortably ride the larger
bike when he was so accustomed to his own.. But it was necessary because it had
the child's seat attached to the back., And he had taken Gabriel,, too.. He could
feel the little head nudge his back,, bouncing gently against him as he rode..
Gabriel was sleeping soundly,, strapped into the seat.. Before he had left the
dwelling,, he had laid his hands firmly on Gab's back and transmitted to him the
most soothing memory he could:. a slow swinging hammock under palm trees on an
island someplace that evening, for the rhythmic sound of languid water lapping
hypnotically against a beach nearby..
As the memory seeped from him into the new child, he could feel Gab's sleep
ease and deepen.. There had been no stir at all, and Jonas lifted him from the
crib and placed him gently into the molded seat.. He knew that he had the
remaining hours of night before they would be aware of his escape., So he rode
hard,, steadily,, willing himself not to tire as the minutes and miles passed..
There had been no time to receive the memories he and The Giver had counted on,
of strength and courage., So he relied on what he had,, and hoped it would be
enough.. He circled the outlying communities,, their dwellings dark..
Gradually, the distances between communities widened, with longer
stretches of empty road.. His legs achd at first;. then,, as time passed,, they
became numb.. At dawn, Gabriel began to stir.. They were in an isolated place;.
fields on either side of the road were dotted with thicket of trees here and
there.. He saw a stream, and made his way to it across a rudded, bumpy meadow;.
Gabriel,, wide awake now,, giggled as the bicycle jolted him up and down.. Jonas
unstrapped Gabe,, lifted him from the bike,, and watched him investigate the
grass and twigs with delight.. Carefully, he hid the bicycle in thick bushes..
"Morning meal,, Gabe!". He unwrapped some of the food and fed them both.. Then he
filled the cup he had brought with water from the stream and held it for Gabriel
to drink.. He drank thirstily himself, and sat by the stream,, watching the new
child play.. He was exhausted.. He knew he must sleep,. resting his own muscles and
preparing himself for more hours on the bicycle.. It would not be safe to travel
in daylight. They'd be looking for him soon.. He found a place deeply hidden in
the trees,, took the new child there,, and lay down,, holding Gabriel in his arms..
Gabe struggled cheerfully as if it were a wrestling game,, the kind they had
played back in the dwelling, with tickles and laughter.. ""Sorry,, Gabe,"," Jonas told
him.. ""I know it's morning,, and I know you just woke up., But we have to sleep now."."
He cuddled the small body close to him, and rubbed a little back., He murmured to
Gabriel soothingly.. Then he pressed his hands firmly and transmitted a memory of
deep,, contented exhaustion..
Gabriel's head nodded, after a moment, and fell against Jonas's chest.. Together,
the fugitives slept through the first dangerous day.. The most terrifying thing was the plains.
By now,, days had passed;. Jonas no longer knew how many.. The journey had become
automatic:. the sleep by days,, hidden in an underbrush and trees;, the finding of
water;, the careful division of scraps of food, augmented by what he could find in
the fields., And the endless,, endless miles on the bicycle by night.. His leg
muscles were taut now.. They achd when he settled himself to sleep., But they were
stronger,, and he stopped now less often to rest.. Sometimes he paused and lifted
Gabriel down for a brief bit of exercise,, running down the road or
through a field together in the dark..
But always,, when he returned, strapping the uncomplaining toddler into the seat
again,, and remounted,, his legs were ready., So he had enough strength of his
own,, and had not needed what The Giver might have provided,, had there been
time.. But when the planes came,, he wished that he could have received the
courage.. He knew there were search planes.. They flew so low that they woke
him with the noise of their engines, and sometimes, looking out and up fearfully
from the hiding places, he could almost see the faces of the searchers.. He knew
that they could not see color, and that their flesh,, as well as Gabriel's light
golden curls,, would be no more than smears of gray against the colorless
foliage.. But he remembered from his science and technology studies at school
that the search planes used heatseeking devices which could identify body warmth
and would hone in on two humans huddled in shrubbery.. So always, when he heard
the aircraft sound,, he reached to Gabriel and transmitted memories of
snow,, keeping some for himself.. Together they became cold;, and when the planes
were gone,, they would shiver,, holding each other, until sleep came again..
Sometimes, urging the memories into Gabriel,. Jonas felt that they were more
shallow,, a little weaker than they had been.. It was what he had hoped, and what
he and The Giver had planned:. that as he moved away from the community,, he would
shed the memories and leave them behind for the people..
But now,, when he needed them,, when the planes came,, he tried hard to cling to
what he still had,, of cold,, and to use it for their survival.. Usually the
aircraft came by day, when they were hiding.. But he was alert at night,, too,,
on the road,, always listening intently for the sound of the engines.. Even
Gabriel listened, and he would call out,, ""Plane!! Plane!"!" sometimes before Jonas
had heard the terrifying noise.. When the aircraft searchers came,, as they did
occasionally, during the night as they rode,, Jonas sped to the nearest tree or
bush,, dropped to the ground,, and made himself and Gabriel cold.,
But it was sometimes a frighteningly close call.. As he pedled through the
nights,, through isolated landscape now, with the communities far behind and no
sign of human habitation around him or ahead,, he was constantly vigilant,,
looking for the next nearest hiding place should the sound of vengeance
come.. But the frequency of the planes diminished.. They came less often, and
flew, when they did come, less slowly,, as if the search had become haphazard and
no longer hopeful.. Finally, there was an entire day and night when they did not come at all.
[Music]